Finding Aid for the Charles Kikuchi Papers LSC.1259
UCLA Library Special Collections
Charles Kikuchi papers
1941-1988
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kikuchi, Charles
LSC.1259
29.0 Linear Feet (58 boxes and 4 oversize boxes)
Charles Kikuchi (1917- ) worked for the California State Employment Service, surveying Nisei occupations. He was recruited by Berkeley sociologist Dorothy Swaine Thomas for the Japanese Evacuation and Relocation Study (JERS). He began to keep a diary and completed field surveys at the Tanforan Assembly Center in Northern California and at the Gila River Relocation Center in Arizona and in 1943 chronicled camp resident settlement in Chicago. He was drafted into the United States Army just before the bombing of Hiroshima. The collection consists of Charles Kikuchi's diaries, correspondence, and related printed material about Japanese Americans and their relocation during World War II. Many diaries include clippings and programs related to the career of Kikuchi's wife, Yuriko Amemiya, a professional dancer and a member of Martha Graham's dance group.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. See the Existence and Location of Copies note for the link to the digitized materials.
Funding
Finding aid and digital representations of archival material funded in part by a grant from the Library Services and Technology Act (LSTA).
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles Kikuchi, 1981-83.
Gift of Yuriko Kikuchi, 1991.
Gift of Warren Tsuneishi, 1981.
Gift of Arthur Hansen, 1989.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942332553606533
Biography/History
Kikuchi was born in 1917 in the San Francisco Bay Area; his father was an Issei barbershop owner; he was placed in an orphanage when he was 8 years old; in 1934 he headed for San Francisco; BA, San Francisco State College, 1939; anonymously published an autobiographical essay, A Young American with a Japanese Face, in Louis Adamic's anthology titled, From Many Lands (1939); worked for the California State Employment Service, surveying Nisei occupations; attended School of Social Welfare, University of California, Berkeley, and received certificate in social work in 1942; recruited by Berkeley sociologist Dorothy Swaine Thomas for the Japanese Evacuation and Relocation Study (JERS); Kikuchi began to keep a diary and completed field surveys at the Tanforan Assembly Center in Northern California and at the Gila River Relocation Center in Arizona; began chronicling camp resident settlement in Chicago, 1943; he was drafted into the United States Army just before the bombing of Hiroshima; received master's degree in social work, New York University (NYU), 1947; worked as a social worker with the Veterans Administration, New York; married Yuriko Amemiya, a professional dancer, in 1946; died September 25, 1988.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of Charles Kikuchi's diaries, correspondence, and related printed material about Japanese Americans and their relocation during World War II. Includes 63 volumes of Kikuchi's original diaries, May 1942-June 1948. Copy diaries span the years 1941-79. Also includes materials related to Kikuchi's work and surveys for the Japanese Evacuation and Relocation Study (JERS) and his study of Japanese American relocation to Chicago, Illinois. Contains various War Relocation Authority (WRA) publications, National Defense Migration reports, various issues of the Gila News Courier, and related publications. Many diaries include clippings and programs related to the career of Kikuchi's wife, Yuriko, a professional dancer and a member of Martha Graham's dance group.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Original diaries (Boxes 1-10).
Copy diaries (Boxes 11-44).
Loose items from diaries (Box 56).
Correspondence and writings (Boxes 45, 57-60, 62).
Japanese Evacuation and Relocation Study (JERS) (Boxes 46-49, 54).
Pacific Coast Committee on American Principles and Fair Play (Box 54).
Photographs and biographical data (Box 54).
Printed material (Boxes 50-53, 62).
Relocation center news publications (Box 55).
Reports (Box 61).
Proclamation documents (Box 61).
Digital Representations Available
Digital image files of the journal of Charles Kikuchi were made from the originals by UCLA's Office of Instructional Development Photographic Services using a Fuji FinePix S1-Pro digital camera with a maximum resolution of 3,040 x 2,016 pixels. The camera was equipped with a Micro-Nikkor flat field lens. Images of the individual pages of the journal were captured as uncompressed 24-bit RGB TIFF files. These archival images were used to create JPEG user images to the specifications of the MoAII viewer.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digitized materials are available electronically at https://digital.library.ucla.edu/catalog/w2339000zz-89112.
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project collection of material about Japanese in the United States (Yuji Ichioka papers) - Collection number 2010. Available at the Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of some of the material from the Charles Kikuchi Papers is available electronically at UCLA Library Digital Collections
Digital reproductions of some of the material from the Charles Kikuchi Papers is available electronically at Calisphere
Diaries.; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Gila River Relocation Center; Kikuchi, Charles--Archives.; Tanforan Assembly Center (San Bruno, Calif.); Yuriko, 1920- .
- Original Diaries
  General note
  Volume [#] = number assigned by the Department of Special Collections
  - May-October 1942. (Box 1, Volume 1-7)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 07, September 1-30, 1942.; (pages 91-346) (Box 1)
  - October-December 1942. (Box 2, Volume 8-14)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 08, October 1-26, 1942.; (pages 1-225) (Volume 8)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 9, October 27-November 3, 1942.; (pages 1-121) (Volume 9)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 10, November 4-9, 1942.; (pages 1-121) (Volume 10)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 11, November 10-17, 1942.; (pages 1-93) (Volume 11)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 12, November 17-25, 1942.; (pages 1-121) (Volume 12)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 13, November 25-December 2, 1942.; (pages 1-120) (Volume 13)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 14, December 3-9, 1942.; (pages 1-121) (Volume 14)
  - December 1942-February 1943. (Box 3, Volume 15-23)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 15, December 10-18, 1942.; (pages 1-118) (Volume 15)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 16, December 20-29, 1942.; (pages 1-119) (Volume 16)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 17, December 30-January 5, 1942.; (pages 1-121) (Volume 17)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 18, January 6-15, 1942.; (pages 1-121) (Volume 18)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 19, January 16-20, 1942.; (pages 1-121) (Volume 19)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 20, January 21-26, 1942.; (pages 1-118) (Volume 20)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 21, January 27-February 2, 1943.; (pages 1-123) (Volume 21)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 22, February 2-9, 1943.; (pages 1-120) (Volume 22)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 23, February 10-15, 1943.; (pages 1-121) (Volume 23)
  - February-April 1943. (Box 4, Volume 24-31)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 24, February 16-23, 1942.; (pages 1-121) (Volume 24)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 25, February 24-27, 1943.; (pages 1-120) (Volume 25)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 26, February 28-March 7, 1943.; (pages 1-121) (Volume 26)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 27, March 9-16, 1943.; (pages 1-121) (Volume 27)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 28, March 16-21, 1943.; (pages 1-120) (Volume 28)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 29, March 22-29, 1943.; (pages 1-120) (Volume 29)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 30, March 29-April 6, 1943.; (pages 1-118) (Volume 30)
    - Charles Kikuchi original diary: Volume 31, April 7-18, 1943.; (pages 1-120) (Volume 31)
  - April-September 1943. (Box 5, Volume 32-39)
  - September 1943-January 1944. (Box 6, Volume 40-46)
  - January 1944-March 1945. (Box 7, Volume 47-[54])
  - August 1945-April 1946. (Box 8, Volume [55]-[58])
  - September 19, 1946-June 19, 1948. (Box 9, Volume [59]-[63])
  - Indexes to diaries., 1941-1947. (Box 10)
- Copy Diaries
  - December 1941-November 1942. (Box 11, Volume 1-3)
  - November 1942-March 1943. (Box 12, Volume 4-6)
  - April 1943-December 1943. (Box 13, Volume 7-9)
  - November 1943-July 1944. (Box 14, Volume 10-12)
  - July 1944-January 1945. (Box 15, Volume 13-15)
  - January-May 1945. (Box 16, Volume 16-18)
  - June-December 1945. (Box 17, Volume 19-21)
  - January 1946-April 1947. (Box 18, Volume 22-24)
  - May 1947-February 1948. (Box 19, Volume 25-27)
  - March 1948-June 1950. (Box 20, Volume 28-30)
  - July 1950-December 1951. (Box 21, Volume 31-33)
  - January 1952-June 1953. (Box 22, Volume 34-36)
  - July 1953-December 1954. (Box 23, Volume 37-39)
  - January 1955-May 1956. (Box 24, Volume 40-42)
  - June 1956-December 1957. (Box 25, Volume 43-45)
  - January 1958-June 1959. (Box 26, Volume 46-48)
  - July 1959-December 1960. (Box 27, Volume 49-51)
  - January 1961-June 1962. (Box 28, Volume 52-54)
  - July 1962-June 1963. (Box 29, Volume 55-56)
  - July 1963-December 1964. (Box 30, Volume 57-59)
  - January 1965-June 1966. (Box 31, Volume 60-62)
  - July 1966-December 1967. (Box 32, Volume 63-65)
  - January-December 1968. (Box 33, Volume 66-67)
  - January 1969-June 1970. (Box 34, Volume 68-70)
  - July 1970-December 1971. (Box 35, Volume 71-73)
  - January 1972-June 1973. (Box 36, Volume 74-76)
  - July 1973-March 1974. (Box 37, Volume 77-79)
  - March 1974-May 1975. (Box 38, Volume 80-83)
  - May 1975-March 1976. (Box 39, Volume 84-86)
  - April-December 1976. (Box 40, Volume 87-89)
  - December 1976-September 1977. (Box 41, Volume 90-92)
  - October 1977-September 1978. (Box 42, Volume 93-95)
  - October 1978-June 1979. (Box 43, Volume 96-98)
  - July-December 1979. (Box 44, Volume 99-100)
- Loose Items from Diaries [Additions, 1989, 1998]
  Loose items from diaries have been foldered. Original box, volume and page numbers of these items are listed below.
  - Box 8, vol.[55]: p. 0(6), 1, 58(2), 207, 232, 262, 270-27/(3). (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - Box 8, vol.[55]: p. 276-277, 291, 293, 309, 314, 320, 327, 341, 361, 372-373, 373, 393(2), 395, 399, 437(6), 453(2), 457. (Box 56, Folder 2)
  - Box 11, vol.1: attached to Charles Kikuchi's letter of, December 20, 1941. (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - Box 11, vol.1: attached to end of vol.[1]. (Box 56, Folder 4)
  - Box 11, vol.2: p. 376, 547, 551, 567(2), 586. (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - Box 11, vol.3: p. 681. (Box 56, Folder 6)
  - Box 12, vol.6: p. 2244, 2303. (Box 56, Folder 7)
  - Box 13, vol.8: p. 2843. (Box 56, Folder 8)
  - Box 13, vol.9: p. 3512, 3554(7). (Box 56, Folder 9)
  - Box 14, vol.10: p. 3624(2). (Box 56, Folder 10)
  - Box 14, vol.12: p. 4741. (Box 56, Folder 11)
  - Box 17, vol.19: p. 8032-8033, 8058-8059, 8074. (Box 56, Folder 12)
  - Box 17, vol.20: Attached to the end of vol.[20]. (Box 56, Folder 13)
  - Box 17, vol.21: p. 79(2), 321. (Box 56, Folder 14)
  - Box 18, vol.22: p. 1272(2), 1307(7). (Box 56, Folder 15)
  - Box 18, vol.22: attached to the end of vol.[22]. (Box 56, Folder 16)
  - Box 18, vol.23: p. 1691(5), 1727, 1764. (Box 56, Folder 17)
  - Box 18, vol.23: sample of Yuriko's credits:, 1944-1946. (Box 56, Folder 18)
  - Box 18, vol.24: Attached to Charles Kikuchi's diary inside of the cover page., (1947) (Box 56, Folder 20)
  - Box 18, vol.24: attachment to program, Martha Graham Dance Company. (Box 56, Folder 21)
  - Box 19, vol.27: attachment to program, Martha Graham Dance Company. (Box 56, Folder 22)
  - Box 20, vol.28: p. 3707. (Box 56, Folder 23)
  - Box 20, vol.29: attached to diary.; attached to diary.; red card inserted, January 6, 1949 January 28, 1949 June 19, 1949. (Box 56, Folder 24)
  - Box 20, vol.30: attached to letter from Yuriko.; Martha Graham Dance Company route sheet attached to letter from Charlie.; attached to diary.; letters from Bobby., February 7, 1950 March 20, 1950 May 12, 1950 (Box 56, Folder 25)
- Correspondence & Writings
  - Correspondence & miscellaneous writings. (Box 45)
  - Correspondence, etc., Early 1980s. (Box 57, Box 58, Box 59, Box 60)
    [Additions, 1989, 1991]
  - Copies of letters., [half legal size document box] (Box 62, Folder 4)
- Japanese Evacuation and Relocation Study (JERS)
  - Chicago case studies of evacuation and relocation, vols.1-14. (Box 46)
  - Chicago case studies of evacuation and relocation, vols.16-32. (Box 47)
  - Chicago case studies of evacuation and relocation, vols.33-46. (Box 48)
  - Chicago case studies of evacuation and relocation, vols.48-50. (Box 49)
    [Volume 47 is UNAVAILABLE.]
  - Case histories taken by Mr. Kikuchi of the following Japanese Americans in the Chicago area. (Box 54)
    Papers donated per Warren Tsuneishi.
    Scope and Contents note
    5. Iwagami, Ichiro
    10. Sawamoto, Chutaro
    35. Ikenaka, Ike
    37. Saruwatari, Akira
    49. Saruwatari, Masako
- Pacific Coast Committee on American Principles and Fair Play
  - Records including minutes and correspondence, of the Pacific Coast Committee on American Principles and Fair Play (of Galen M. Fisher., as sometime secretary of the Committee)., 1941-45 (Box 54)
    Papers donated by Warren Tsuneishi given to him by Kikuchi.
- Photographs and Biographical Data [Additions, 1989]
  - 10 prints made from originals retained by Mrs. Charles Kikuchi, of Charles Kikuchi., and accompanying biographical information., ca. 1938-1944 (Box 54)
    Papers donated by Professor Arthur Hansen.
- Printed Materials
  - Government publications relating to the Japanese. (Box 50, Box 51)
  - Various printed items. (Box 52)
  - Various publications by Japanese Americans, mostly copies of Trek [Utah Relocation Center newspaper]. (Box 53)
  - Newsprint items: newsletters, clippings., [half legal size document box] (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - Theater program., 1988.; [half legal size document box] (Box 62, Folder 4)
- Relocation Center News Publications [Additions, 1989, 1998]
  - Totalizer - Tanforan Assembly Center, California, vol.I nos.2-9., May 23-July 11, 1942. (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Totalizer - Tanforan Assembly Center, California, vol.I, nos.11-18., July 18-September 5, 1942. (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - Totalizer - Tanforan Assembly Center, California, vol.I no.19., September 12, 1942.; 6 copies. (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - Desert Sentinel, vol.II., October 22, 1943.; 1 item. (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - Relocator News Week, vol.I nos.2-3, 5 and 11., October 14-December 23, 1943. (Box 55, Folder 5)
  - Gila Coop News - Rivers, Arizona, vol.I nos. 5, 6, 8, 9, 11, 13, 18 and 19., July 20-October 26, 1943. (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - Gila News Courier - Rivers, Arizona, vol.I nos.1-34., September 12-December 29, 1942. (Box 55, Folder 7)
  - Gila News Courier - Rivers, Arizona, vol.II nos.1-29., January 1-March 9, 1943. (Box 55, Folder 8)
  - Gila News Courier - Rivers, Arizona, vol.II nos.30-53 and 55-59., March 11-May 18, 1943. (Box 55, Folder 9)
  - Gila News Courier - Rivers, Arizona, vol.II nos.60-62, 64-80, 83-84, 86-87, 89-90, 92-98 and 100., May 20-August 21, 1943. (Box 55, Folder 10)
  - Gila News Courier - Rivers, Arizona, vol.III nos.1-5, 8-11, 13-16 and 18-37., August 24-November 16, 1943. (Box 55, Folder 11)
  - Gila News Courier - Rivers, Arizona, vol.III nos.40-50, 52-70, 72-76 and 95., November 23-March 30, 1944. (Box 55, Folder 12)
- Reports
  - Bob Spencer Gila reports, vol.1., 1942-43.; Fragile carbons in large binder. (Box 61, Folder 1)
    Kikuchi copy.
  - Gila report - Ivers, Arizona, vol.2., April 1943.; Fragile carbons and mimeograph sheets in large binder. (Box 61, Folder 2)
- Proclamation Documents
  - Letter, copies of proclamation documents, [half legal size document box] (Box 62, Folder 1)
  - Copies of proclamation documents, etc., [half legal size document box] (Box 62, Folder 2)